So we started with the
programming class.  We continue with the
programming class.  Last week we
were working with, uh,
control structures, the use of
control structures.  Today what we are going
to do is enter the fourth
unit called class development.
So, in class development we will
first look at what a class is.
First, let's do a first
review to get our bearings, okay?  Because what I'm
going to do in these next two
hours is very abstract and I need it to
be clear, okay?  I need to
explain it well so that you understand it
correctly and know what is
going to happen.  Okay, uh, code
reuse,
period Python.  So I say, for
example, print.
Hello, uh, hello, hello, hello, Pepe, okay?
Hello, Pepe.  And then I say, print,
how are you?
And I'm going to say print.
You know, you're 45,
okay?  And then this is a block of
three print statements and that's it.
Okay, so now I come and say,
"Hey, Juan, you're 34
years old."  Print, hello Jorge,
you're 56 years old, okay?  I can make
as many prints as I want.  The problem
is that when I start making
a lot of prints, I have the impression that
I am wasting my time.  I
have the impression that I
could group this code, I could
encapsulate it, I could reuse the
code in a way that would be more efficient.
One way to encapsulate the code
we saw earlier is to
create functions, functions to
encapsulate.
So I come over here and say, "Okay,
yeah, say hi."
And then this bled.  And so
now I can say hello as many times
as I want
and right from the start on the screen I say,
"Okay, okay, here it seems that I'm
starting to save, okay? Save
effort, but there's still a small
problem. The small problem there is,
let's see it.
The small problem there is,
Python 3, uh, 002, okay? The problem is
that it always says PP, with which
nothing happens because the functions can be
customized, okay? So the
functions 003 uh parameters of the
function
are customized through parameters.
So I can put name, comma,
age and then I say hello, comma, name
and so you know that you have to
know that you have age, years, which
means that here I put Juan and
here I put Jorge
and here I put Jaime.
Okay? And then I execute
Python 3
and then I finish customizing the
function. Okay? So in computer science
there is a there is always a rule, a
constant, a continuous tendency
over time which is to reuse. In
Computer science, we are lazy, we want to
work little, we as human beings want to
work as little as
possible and for the machine to work as
much as possible, okay? Because
human beings have feelings, we get
tired, okay? The machine doesn't. Well, what we
want is for the machine to work,
okay? Well, once we have completed
this review, this is what we have
learned or part of what we have learned
in previous units, now what
we are going to do next is learn one more level of grouping, one more level of encapsulation and that level is called object-oriented programming through this concept called classes. So for this, so for this I am going to do the following. I am going to
start teaching
classes with something that is cats,
okay?
So with cats, with cats what
we are going to do is the following. I
come here and say class cat
and everything that happens here inside will be
part of a cat. When we create a
class, next we have to
define a very special method
called init. Now, when we get to
Constructors, I'll explain the
inite method.
Okay, I'll put it for now and I'll
explain it better later.
And now
what I'm going to say next is put self. Self
is myself, okay? Self puncor,
self.
And self dot uh, well, I don't know.
Cat breed, okay? Let's say, this means
I'm creating an
abstract capsule. This is what I want to
tell you,
okay? And inside that abstract capsule,
I'm going to put properties for now.
Now next 05 I create a first
cat.
So I come over here and say cat 1
equals cat.
Print
cat 1. And what's going to happen on the
screen,
what's going to happen on the screen, ah,
look, it was right here,
what's going to happen on the screen
is uh Python 3. And what was I going to tell you?
Where are you? 005 and I create a cat. Okay,
nothing happens, okay? Because what I'm going to do
is say that this is equal to nothing
and this is equal to nothing and this is equal to
nothing. Okay, that's it.
And it tells me, "Okay, you have a
cat." Okay, so from this moment on, the program recognizes
an entity
called cat. The program doesn't know if
this is an animal or what it is, okay? But it
knows that as a programmer, I have defined
something that from this moment on will be
called cat. Okay, now
next,
well, I can not only create one cat,
006, I can create as many cats as I want.
So now next, I say,
cat 2 is equal to cat, print me
cat 2 and therefore, and therefore,
Python 3, and uh, let's see, do I have Franco
Candel? I
no longer have Fran Cendel, okay? Uh, so
006, okay? And now I have two cats.
Now I have two programming cats.
Okay, so once I have this, now
next, what I'm going to do is the
following. We're going to continue with the
members that a class has, and from
there, we'll go with, uh, creating
properties, creating methods, and
creating constructors. Okay?
I'm going here, I'm going to  structure, I'm going
to exercises, I'm going to 006,
001 eh members.
So, a class has something
called a constructor method.
The constructor
is called when the object is instantiated.
A class,
a class has properties, they are
static in the sense that they don't
move, they don't execute any action. And
now from there, a class has
methods. For example, if I have a
cat, a method would be Mauluya. So
from ma self
and the cat says meow. So
print meow.
Now next if I have a cat,
that means cat 1 point mauya.
Let's see it.
And this is now we've
changed folders.
Visibility, exercises.
terminal
and Python 3 001,
okay? And the cat says meow. Therefore,
a method
is an action that the object performs. That
is, a property is something static,
a method is something dynamic, okay? It's
something that moves between quotes, let
's say, so to speak.
Okay, so these are the
main members of a class. There's one
issue that  It has to do with
visibility, which is the following.
002,
visibility
of the members.
And then I say cat one is equal to
this, okay? And now I say cat 1 pun eh
color is equal to orange.
And now print.
The cat
is colored.
Cat 1 color.
If I now execute this code, this
means that Python 3
00.
Here 002,
okay? The cat is orange, that
is,
the visibility,
the visibility by default is public,
which means that from outside,
from outside I can write
the property
and from outside I
can read the property,
which is not very good, the truth
is not very good because you will say, "Hey, how
cool, I can enter and I can write and I
can read." Well, we are not supposed to be
able to do that
because the idea of ​​creating capsules,
the idea of ​​creating containers seems
not, but in a certain way it is to protect the
information, encapsulate the information,
save the information so that later it cannot be
accessed. And you
will say, "Wow, well if not  I can
access that information, what
use is it to me?   Let's
see, I think that for someone to enter,
well, it seems that there isn't.  Okay, the point
is that this information should only be accessible
in the way we
have established, that is, in the
method, according to the method we have
established.  So for that,
for that we're going to do a first
test there.  There you will now see the Python
Object Set private
property.
Okay.  And let's see,
okay?  From
Vale, this
and Okay, okay, okay.  Okay, yes, but
properties.  Hang on a minute.  Let's go
here to chat GPT and Python set private
property
on object.  And we see that there are different
tricks.  Okay,
okay.  There is no real
private property as in other
stricter languages.  There's one, okay, there's one, there's
a convention,
but here's the double, okay?, which is
mangling, that is, accidentally preventing the
user from accessing
a property.  Well, here we go.
Now let's talk about this
property setter getter,
okay?  Well, 003
private property.
Okay, I'm
going to say in color next, okay?  In
color I'm going to say that I don't want
this property to be accessible,
so I do self color, double score color,
okay?
And now if I try to do this from outside
, I try to write the color or read the
color, what's going to happen here,
Python 3 003, what's going to happen EPA
here, wait.  Python 3.
Well, it tells me yes, even though it's
not supposed to be able to, but okay.
Well, he should have told me
no, okay, but anyway, it's a way of
trying to make properties
private.  Now, later you will see that
not always, but in some
circumstances we may be interested in making
the properties of objects
private so that they cannot be accessed
from outside.  Sorry.  Yes, well, it
cannot be accessed from outside.  and
can only be accessed with the access keys
that we build ourselves.
Let's go deeper into
object-oriented programming.
Let's see it.
And we're going to create properties.
Okay, the properties, as we were
talking about a moment ago,
001 properties,
right?  They are the ones that allow us to
establish what is happening with a
cat.  Self.  Name
defaults to nothing.
I'm going to return color
and self dot whatever we want, okay?
Self point because eye color.
Eye color.
Properties, as we see,
are therefore the attributes that a class has,
the pieces of information that it
will store at a given time.
Once we have properties,
we will see that, as we saw before, we
also have methods.  Now,
methods 002,
meow method,
okay?  Creating methods
001,
meow method.
Okay, methods are defined as
functions, but a method
eh cat 1 equals cat and cat 1 pun
meow.  This works,
but it shouldn't work.
Let's see it.
Rather, it shouldn't be structured
like this.
Python 3
and
here 001. Okay, the meow method.  What
happened?  Cat.
What happened?
Do you mean cat?  Ah, cat one point
meow, sorry.  Okay, there it is.  And neither.
Cat has no attribute.  Oh, sorry, it's
Mauluya, not meow.
Okay, come on.  And this is a method,
right?
Now, once we have this, we
can create as many methods as we
need, but remember that I mentioned this to you
with the functions, that 002
function with return.  The function should not
do a print, but the function should
always do a return.
Return meow.  And so here I'm going to
put print
gato maulya
and
print 002.
The result is the same, so
you'll say, well,
what we've actually done is the
same.  But not really, okay?   It's
actually much cleaner on the inside
than a method that returns with return
instead of doing a print.
Next,
we are now going
to talk about the set methods and the
get methods.
The set and get methods are a very
advisable and very clean way to create an
access interface to
whatever we really want, right?
Well, to our objects, to
our properties, to everything for that,
for example, to show you an example
of how a setter works.  And
now I want to change the
color of the cat or the age of the cat.  So
death set age.
Death set age
self coma new age.  And then I say
self pun age equals new age.
So if I
want to put the cat's age, cat 1.
age
is 1. I could also say cat 1 pun
age equals 1, but
this is not recommended.
This is much safer.
Because?  Well, for a very
simple reason,
they both do the same thing, but there is a
difference and that is, how old is the
cat?  Print.
Right now the cat is about
one point old, years old.
And after doing this operation,
let's see how old the cat is,
okay?  Hey, Python 3
setter, okay?  Right now the cat is
0 years old and right now the cat is one
year old.
But what would happen if 004
were setting
without control?
What would happen if I now said, "The
cat is 5 years old?"  Well, of course,
from a logical point of view,
right now the cat is 0 years old, right now
the cat is 5 years old.  Wait.
At what point does an animal suddenly turn 5
years old?  It seems that something
is not working properly.
Okay?  Why do we make methods
instead of directly setting the
properties of objects?  Well, for
several reasons, but one very
simple reason to understand is that if
we use methods we can establish
validation mechanisms, but if we don't
use methods it is difficult to establish
validations.  So because of this, because of
this, now next I'm going to
say
I'm going to say
if
self punity is equal to new is equal to
new
age -1.
In that case,
self-puned age equals new age.
Els,
print or return, okay?  Whatever,
print,
operation not permitted.
So if I now try to
set Python 3004 without control, not operation not
allowed, you can't do that.  Okay?
I mean, let's take this out,
let's take this out,
okay?  And I'm going to say 005
control on set.  What do methods allow us
?  It allows us to establish
control mechanisms to ensure that
the logic applied to the
computer program is a logic that makes
sense, is a logic that is
predictable and that really helps us
work correctly.  Okay?  Let's
see.
Well,
we have methods.  Let's now make a
get method 006,
a getter
in the same way.   I
do this.  Death get age
self
and I say eh return
self.ad.
How old is the cat?  Well, I
shouldn't say age, but rather I should say
get age.  And I should say get old.
You might also say to me, "Yeah,
but why bother if it was already
working for you before, why
bother creating a method?"  Well,
although the method currently does
the same thing
as directly accessing the property,
from an
information security perspective,
using get and set methods
allows us to establish a series of
security mechanisms that we did
n't have before, right?  Now if we
want them, only if we want them, then we
can have them.
Next we are going to talk about
constructors.  The constructor now
is the special method that appears
here called init.  This special method
is called a constructor and is an
occur method, a method that is
always executed at the beginning, that is, always
when an object is created.  And one of the
things,
one of the things,
this is 001 constructor
most interesting is that 002
constructor with parameters.  So
I, for example,
will remove this below.
I'm going to say init self comma new color
comma new age.
Color is new color, new age is
new age.  So, so
now I can say that cat 1
equals cat.  And by the way, in the builder's signature
I see that he invites me to put a
new orange color and the age 0 years.
What's going on?  That way I save
time, that way I save effort,
okay?  So what I do is,
since I create a cat, since we're
here, I tell it that it's orange
and I tell it that it's age is zero and
in this case, it doesn't need to initialize
the parameters.  I don't have to
initialize all of them.  Really, if you
notice, it's silly to give
a cat a zero when it's created.  Let's
see, maybe not.  Okay, I mean,
if this app,
okay?
Hey, age is meaningless if we're covering
the birth of a cat.  Imagine it
is an application in which the
object, the cat, is created when it is born.  It doesn't
make sense, okay?  003,
not all parameters
in the constructor.   I
can tell you, look, I do want the color
, but age isn't important.
Because when the cat is born it is 0 years old.   You
don't need to put it in the
constructor for me.  I can tell you this.  But
what would happen if I had a
computer application for a
cat shelter and it brought me a
5-year-old cat?  Of course, I'm not going to
tell him, "No, no, either you bring it to me that's 0
years old or don't bring it to me because my
computer program can't fit it in
five."  Okay?  Well, if I were to make a
program for a cat shelter, I
would have to allow that
when a cat is registered in the
shelter, it is not 0 years old, because they
might have brought it to me when the cat
was already grown.  Okay?
Good.  All of this has to do
with the creation, right?, with the
creation of classes.  Now we will do an
exercise to see how this is applied.
And now you'll see that this doesn't seem like it,
but it has its application, right?  It has
its very strong application.  Before that,
well, using classes and objects,
okay?  This is what we were doing
a moment ago and that is using
classes and objects,
right?  Creation 001
multiple instances.
Let's do an exercise,
okay?  Cat one is an orange cat and cat
two is a black cat.  Okay, so
before we get into using
inherited classes, let's do a
serious exercise in which I
'm going to simplify the class as much as
possible, okay?  In which, what I
hope, what I want is for us to
easily understand what
object-oriented programming is going to be useful for.  And
for this I'm going to do an exercise in
which we create a computer application
that works with clients.
So so so I
'm going to create 002 client application
or client practice exercise.
I insist, I'm going to make it as simple as
possible.  I'm going to take this off.  I'm going to take
this off.  Okay.  And I say class client.
I create a client
and the client will only have,
let's simplify it as much as possible,
name
equals new name
and self.email,
email, equals new
email.
equals new email.
So
what I'm going to do now, once
we've defined the class, is uh, create a
microprogram that uses this class.
Look, if you want, I'll say self-
punction
equals direction,
okay?  And sorry, new address.
and new direction.
Okay, so
once I've done that, I
'm going to do the following next.
003.
Now user input
and I say, eh, print
program clients by José Vicente
Carratalá
and I say,
ah, input,
input
Enter
a client's email.
Input enters a customer's address
.
Ah, sorry, sorry, sorry.
Customer name,
customer email
and customer address.
Okay?  And then, and then I say the
following,
uh, client one equals client
and to the client I give the new name,
comma, the new email,
comma, the new address
and that's it.  I mean, I'm telling you, I
've already told you that this was going to be easy.
This is the first exercise.  This
exercise will obviously grow later,
okay?  This exercise will later become
longer and more complicated, but for
now what I have achieved
is to create a client structure, no longer
saving as we did until now, three
independent variables,
independent, three
different variables, three variables that had no
relationship with each other, okay?  But
what we've done is group them into
the same structure, okay?  And now
next and now next,
finally, of course, I can't do a
print client, uh, print client because it
will just give me the
memory address, okay?  Print client 1,
okay?
Uh, I run
Python 3 and 00
4 and it's going to tell me, "Hey, the cat, what
what cat or what cat? Where are we?
Creating methods. No, not here, we're
not here.
Okay. Okay. Use here. Print
client, okay?
And Python 3 and 004.
Okay. Enter the name José
Vicente with José Vicente. The email
info@jocarsa.com
and the address. This address tells me,
"You have a client, okay?  You have a
client saved there in memory,
also at this address in
RAM.  Okay, okay, I'm not saying no, but
I want to see it next.  So,
well, let's see if I can see it.
Oh, let's see if the case method catches me.
Let's see.  005.
Uh, scroll through keys.
Moment, moment.  I say for
eh key in client 1. Casse
print
key.  I think this is going to tell me
what flowers.  Um, Python
tiki tiki tiki and B key.  Momentin.  Ah,
let's see.  Hey, Python
and loop in object case.
Okay, okay, okay, okay.  Ah, fantastic.
This, come on, this is what Vale, this
is what I was missing.  Case.  Gee,
I said.  Okay, this, this and this.  Okay,
no.  Wow, it's customer one.   Let's
see,
wait,
wait.
Skis.
Let's see, let's
see.  Incredible key.  You'll see.
Well, client is noter volv.  Okay,
let's see why. Of
course, I don't have a dictionary.  Clear.
Let's see,
literals.  Okay, yeah, but wow.   Phew
.  Okay, okay, okay.  This is it, this is it.
Okay, I can't
explain this much to you, I can't explain it
in depth right now because this
is part of unit six,
storage structures, okay?  So
I don't want to give away any information,
but let's see.  This, this and this.
Okay, now yes.  Good.  So, so
I say uh the key piece of information
,
okay?
Uh, uh, key client 1.
And then now next and
that concludes this little
demonstration exercise.
Name, José Vicente.  Email
info@jocarsa.com.
Heading towards José Vicente Street.
And no, let's see, one key client.
Wait, what's going on?  Customer a
key point.
Let's see, here it goes again.  José Vicente
info@jocarsa.com,
José Vicente's street.
Well,
what's going on?
Ah, wow, key dictation.  This is what
happens.
Okay, come on.
Okay, José Vicente,
uh, info@jocarsa.com,
José Vicente's street.  Now yes, the
piece of information named José
Vicente is worth it.  The email information piece
is info@carsa.  The address information piece
is José
Vicente Street.  Okay?  What does this mean?
Well, I insist, this little demonstration
for now tells us that
we'll be able to use classes to
store blocks of information, okay?
To save more advanced pieces of
information that will ultimately be
useful for a lot of things.  Okay,
and now finally in this block, before
, as I said before, dedicating a
part of the class to dealing with the topic of
activities and assessment and
all that, we're going to talk about
inherited classes.  Inherited classes
are classes, that is, they are a
tool that allows us to have an
inheritance mechanism and inheritance
basically deals with transmitting
information from one class to another.
For this, for this I am going to
use inherited classes and within
the inherited classes I am going to say the
following.  Let's get back to the cat.  Let's
go back to the concept of the cat.  001 class
cat dot Python
and I'm going to say class cat
eh, death init
self.
Okay, and I'm going to say here that, uh, we're
going to see self pun color is, uh, well, I don't
know, it's equal to zero.  Okay?  What's going on?
Well, the cat can have a
self.   It
is equal to zero.  Color, for example,
would be nothing.  And now let's imagine that I
also have 002 the dog class, so
class dog and I say init
and then the dog has color and the
dog has age.  And here I begin to
see a problem from a
programming perspective,
which is that there are repeated properties and we
already know that when
something is repeated in programming, it's not cool, right?   We do
n't want anything to happen again.
So, when we don't want
something to be repeated,
what we can do in this case in
object-oriented programming
is to create a parent class, a
class that contains the other two in
this way.  003,
mother relative class, okay?  A
parent class.  I'm going to create an animal class
and the animal class will have self color and
self age.  And now next
here inside cat I'm going to say that the
cat is an animal.
Clash cat, clas
dog
is also animal class.   What
happens this way is that
now I'm going to put su here
and here I'm going to put su.
S means superclass and superclass
means that from this class I go
to the higher class.  The top class
is this one, and I catch everything that
class has.
If all goes well.  Now next,
well, I'm going to start compiling, okay?
which right now wouldn't give me much of a
mistake, I think,
but no, never say never.
I come here,
open
Python 3003 terminal,
okay?  And everything is OK.  Good.  And now, and
now next
I say, eh, cat 1 equals cat.
Wow, cat 1 equals cat.  And print
cat 1
point age.  This is 003004
using the parent class.
If I now say Python 3004,
ow.  Hey, cat doesn't have a moment.  S s sp
s.
I have some mistake here.  Momentin.
Eh, error
s
of If there is any error it must be the super.
Mm.
Okay.
Ah, wow.  Okay, super init.
Okay, now yes.  Good.  Super init and super
init.  Okay.  Okay, let's see.
We recharge and it tells us, "Your cat is 0
years old."  But the funny thing about this, the
funny thing about this is that, eh,
as I would say, do you realize that a
cat has no age?
Cat has inherited the age of animal and
dog has inherited the age of animal.  The
fun thing
about class inheritance is that you
can increase class inheritance
as much as you want, because for example,
now I say 005 rock, right?  And
so now I say,
"Okay, class rock.
rock and I say from init, obviously,
okay? And I say the rock, a rock doesn't
have an age, okay? Well, although
technically it could have, but
let's say it doesn't have an age. I say, self. X
is equal to 0, it's the position at x in
space self.Y
and self. Z. But of course, what happens?
Well, I say, "Wait, for an animal to be
able to move in space it would also
have to have x, y and z.  So I do
this,
I put them here, but once again we
run into the same problem and that is that
animal and rock
are duplicating the same parameters and
that will result in
inefficiency for me, but I can make as many
inheritances as I want.
So, 006, top level of
inheritance.
So I come over here and I'm going to
create a top class still called
object.
And the object class is going to have a defit
in which in the object class
I am going to put x, y and z.  And I'm going to say that the
rock class inherits from object and the
animal class inherits from object.  So there's
no need, let's see, there's no
need to
say here that both one class and the
other, sorry, not here,
not here.  Now yes.  Hello, Lucas, good
afternoon.  This one has superinit and this one
has superinit.  So, uh,
sorry, this shouldn't go here, this
should go here.
So the object has x, y, z
and the rock, when inheriting from the object, has
x, y, z and the animal has x, y, z.
But I'll tell you more.  An object is a
physical object, right?  But object could in
turn be a child of a superclass called
concept or entity, right?  The element.
There are objects that can be physical,
tangible, an object, a table, a
chair and there are objects that can be
intangible, okay?  the truth, the
joy.  But of course, what position in the
space X Y Z does truth or
joy or sadness have?  Not applicable, but
they may have a name.  So the idea with
this is that the
object-oriented programming methodology, the
class-based programming methodology, can greatly help us
represent problems that
can arise in the real world.  This class,
as I say, is very theoretical,
okay?  It seems very theoretical, but
nevertheless, but nevertheless, now
we are going to do a series of
exercises.  The thing is, working
with objects without having yet worked on
unit 5 and unit 6 is difficult
because I have to create objects without having
worked on storage structures.
Well, I also tell you that when
we get to the unit the fun will
obviously start to increase.
Okay?  Before we get into
the second half of today's
programming class, let's
talk for a moment about
activities and assessment, shall we?  And
so, as you slowly begin to
have questions, I also
take advantage of the classes to
give you answers, because, well, the
questions, whether you like it or not,
start to repeat themselves, which is normal,
obviously.
Let's see.  Good.  And here we go.
Look,
okay, being in a training cycle,
on the one hand, okay?  In a training cycle
we have the teaching of content.
On the one hand,
theoretical content is taught,
which is what I'm doing right
now, and two, exercises are done,
okay?  In class,
in class, in which the teacher
shows the applied concepts.  Okay, and
those of you
in the room, in the class, are given the opportunity to
participate, ask questions, propose,
modify, all of this, okay?  What it
has within what is the
online methodology, well, what it has, let's
say, the live session, the
collective tutoring and there is eventual
interaction
in class, which is the
collective tutoring.
Okay, wait until I save this,
okay?  evaluation
dot txt.
And as I tell you, and as I tell you, well, in
turn, I'm going to go for a moment to a
program made in Python
and I come now here, I execute, I
tell it, there, wait for it to open
in the other window, I
tell it that I want to open
programming, right?  Let's see.  Lady lady
first,
uh, programming.  Okay, now.  Okay.
Generate, copy.
Okay, and now, for example, well
now what we're going to do is
this is what we've seen in class
so far, up to unit
four.
Do a cumulative exercise.
Create the activity statement only
with what we have seen so far,
without giving away any content.
Okay, let's go.
Let's look at
the system now.
What you are doing is analyzing what
we have seen in class, analyzing the
exercise, the exercises, the
knowledge that we have shown in
class and you are going to propose an exercise,
okay?  An exercise, a non-
assessable, non-scorable activity, which
we developed here in class to
show.
Let's see.
Okay, details of the statement.  Sometimes it
takes longer, sometimes it takes less time to
think.  Okay, come on, an activity.
Let's see.  100 consoles, no files
or collections.  Includes entry and exit.   Mini
shelter manager.  Okay, that's cool.
Uh, create a little
console program.  Look, an animal shelter.
Okay, I love it.  Perfect.  Let's go for
it.  Inheriting an animal class.  The
program will request user information,
apply validations, classify
animals by age, and display a file
for each one.  Okay, I really like this.
Class eh animal base class, okay?  Okay,
okay, okay.  Classes, daughters, cat and dog.
Okay, very good.  Very catomuya and
barking dog, obviously he had all the appearance.
Okay,
define constants in uppercase.
At the end of the data entry,
Conert assures that no age is negative,
right?  Exception, when you read the ages
from input, convert it to int in a try
except fine.
Displays an initial message with your
name, asking the user for the color of the cat and
dog, breed of the cat and dog,
initial age of the cat and dog.  Okay.
Looping and operations.  Simulates the passage of
time.
How old do you want to pretend?  Okay,
auxiliary functions, milk.  What a great
workout.  Okay, well,
here we go.
My goodness.  Okay, let's see.  Let's go
there.  Let's do this exercise little by little
.  He tells us, we're going to make
software for a shelter and he tells us,
we're going to do the initial class.  Okay,
so I'm like you guys right now
.  I have found an activity
and I have to do it.  And if the program
says I have to do this, then I
have to do this, okay?   Let's
go there.
I come this way.  Use, okay?  And eh
new file 007 and cumulative exercise
point Python.
Let's go there
and I'll follow instructions.
Create the base class animal.
Class animal.
Public properties.  color, string,
age, integer starts at zero.  So
death init
self
self pun color equals string
self pun age equals cer integer.
Okay, with this I just Ah, careful.
Private property, wait for it.  Ah,
private property, chain race.  Okay.
Okay.  Race
is a chain.
Parameterless constructor that
initializes default values.
initializes default values.  Okay?
Methods.  I'm following the exercise.
I tell you now 008
methods.
What do you want?  Well, def set age.
self comma new age
only allows the age to be increased by
exactly one.  If self pun
age is equal to new age -1, if self
age is equal to new age -1, then
self pun age plus equals 1. It only
allows increasing the age if the age
meets this condition.  Get old.
Def get age
eh def get age self
return self.
And the same with set race and get race.
Okay, so def set race
self dot comma new race
and then self pun race is equal to
new race
and description well and get race, sorry,
def get race
self is return
self
uh race.
And finally, and finally it returns, it doesn't
print, it returns return, okay?
returns
def description
return
eh self pun
age plus
str
color
plus
self dot
Rafa, okay?  For example,
with this I have almost fulfilled the first
point, okay?  I've almost accomplished the first
point and added a doc string to the class or
some method explaining what it does.
Okay, so let's add a little doc
string.  A 2 3 1 2 3. Animal class
defines age, color and breed.  Okay, a
little doc string that tells us what
to expect from that class.
What I'm doing, as I said,
is reading the statement of an activity
that has been set up based on the
exercises we've done, okay?  And
now continue.  Classes, daughters, cat and
dog, okay?  009 daughter classes.
So I come over here, I'm going to put
another doc string up here.
Shelter program,
copyright 2025
copyright 2025 José Vicente Carratalá.  And
this program eh manages a shelter,
okay?  So
def cat is an animal,
that is, cat inherits from animal and dog
inherits from animal.  So def cat and
def dog inherit from animal.
Its constructors,
its constructors
call super init.
Their constructors
call super init, but each of
them has its own method, so
def ma
self
prints print
meow
and def ladra
de Ladra self
print wow
gu no guow
valo es insist what I am doing as I
read an exercise and I am
building what is asked of me
now define constants in capital letters
for example max age cat, max age
dog
And at the end of the data entry,
secure with assert.  Okay, so
let's see, it displays an
initial message with your name, print.  Okay, ask
the user for age, the initial age and
check that age,
okay?  No, it's not going to get through
this.  Very good.  Well, here we go, 010.
Let's continue
with the exercise.
Hey, do you want me to define a maximum
cat age?  Max age of dog.  Well, I define
age plus cat and age max dog.  I do
what the statement tells me.  Sometimes it
seems strange, but for now I do it.
Assertion.  Well, I can assert.
We'll see at the end of the entry,
but we haven't made an entry yet.
Okay.  And when you read input, okay.  I show
an initial message with your name.  Print.
Print.  Hello, I'm José Vicente.
Hello, I'm José Vicente
and welcome to my refuge.
Okay.  Asks user
cat color equals input.  Enter
the color of the cat.
Dog color.
Enter the dog's color,
breed,
and age.
Let's see.
Yes, but but
okay, okay, okay, okay, let's see, just a
moment, just
a moment.
Okay, okay, okay.  Okay, let's see,
dog equals dog.
and cat equals cat.
So now
color point cat
and color point dog.
Okay, now
breed point cat
is breed point dog.
and breed point dog.
Okay.  And eh, let's see, and what am I missing,
what am I missing, what do you want me to
put
and the age.
Cat point age dog point age age
age.
Okay,
define constants.  Okay, okay, okay.
Display by console.  Okay.
If age, now I say, if cat dot
age is less than one,
print.
The cat is a puppy.
If cat dot age is greater than or equal to
one and less than if
print
the cat is a young adult.
If the cat is greater than or equal to seven,
then the cat is an adult.
Same with the dog.  I'm doing
what they ask me to do.
If dog
point age,
if dog point age,
if dog point age.
Okay.  Okay.
Now, loop simulates the passage of time
for the cat.  They're asking for just the
cat, so I say, "Okay,
increase its age until it reaches the
age the user specified."  For
example,
eh, maximum age
is equal to input.   Just
a moment.  How old do you want to
pretend?
And this is an integer.
And then I now say for age in
range from zero to maximum age
and I say, let's see and I say cat dot
set age
age.
Okay, create a free format function
for the date, whatever, okay?  And there is a
list of things we have to
do.  Print.  I'm going to say cat.  Age,
while we're at it, okay?  And we execute.
Let's run
clear now.
And this is Python 3010.
Okay.  And that's it.  What does it say?  New age
minus1.
Ah, okay.  Ah, yes.  The if, the if, this if,
if, I'm missing two points.  Okay.
Okay.
Expected points.  From set race.  Set race.
Set race.  Two points here.  Okay.
Okay.
If cat, age ang cat dot age.
I always make the same mistake.
A dog.  Age.   I
detect my mistakes.
And dog is an animal.  Animal.  Animal.
Animal.  Dog is Oops.  Wait a minute.
Wait a minute.  Dog equals
dog.
Wow.  Wait.
43.
Au.
Let's see.
Positioning error.
Let's look at it
because it tells me there's a
positional error there, but it doesn't make sense to me that there's
a positional error.
Ah, how?
No, no, wait, wait until I
see the mistake.
Animal cat clash.
Ah, okay.  Okay, I'm missing the self.
Incredible.
Okay.  Hey, wait a minute, look, let's
get this.
Okay.  Okay, okay, okay.  And
okay, okay.  Cat color, orange.
Dog color, eh, black.
Enter the cat breed.  No, no, I don't
know about races.  Siamese.  The boxer dog breed
.  Age one.  Dog age one.
How old do you want to pretend for the cat?
15.
The cat is now 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10
to 15. Cat's profile, age 15,
orange color, Siamese breed.  Dog profile,
age one, black, boxer breed.
Public properties, black color age
one.  And so on.  Okay, so,
well, we see how, as I said,
the activity would take a little longer to
complete, but you get the idea, right?
So the idea is that there will be eventual
interaction, so from
here on,
from here on we
move on to the evaluation phase.
Assessment is
carried out through
activities
that result in practical programming exercises
where possible.
Where possible, it means that
there are units that have
theoretical content, and obviously, those
units that have theoretical content,
well, it's less easy to do exercises on
this code, right?  Okay, so here we
go.   Just
a moment.
Okay, wait
a minute.
Let's see,
a second-rate one.
Okay, so from here on
the evaluation phase serves two
purposes.
On the one hand,
in terms of the training cycle,
learning
and development must be recorded.
of the student and the achievement
of the intended learning outcomes
.
On the other hand, let's see it here,
okay?  On the other hand,
activities
are an important part
of showing
yourself whether you are really
learning
or not.  That is, in class
you copy my code,
but in the activities
you start creating code.
From here, therefore,
first there is class and then there
is this concept of carrying out
activities, where as I say,
on the one hand I must have a
record, a record of these
activities
because a training cycle results in
the granting of a qualification
with official recognition and this
qualification must be granted once the
student has demonstrated having achieved a
series of knowledge, okay?, through
a series of results of that
learning.  And on the other hand, as I
say, since computer science is very
thankless in the sense that you put in a
lot of effort and you don't know if you're
learning or not, the activities
are a way of showing yourselves whether you
're learning or
not.  Okay?  Next, once
we've talked about this, we talk about
the role of artificial intelligence
in teaching,
in teaching
and assessment.
I have a philosophical principle, a
philosophical, ethical principle, whatever you want to
call it, that says that artificial intelligence
should not
replace human beings,
because then nothing good will happen,
okay?
If humans allow themselves to be replaced
by artificial intelligence,
artificial intelligence
must help humans achieve
things they would otherwise be unable to
achieve.  That is to say, for me,
in my opinion,
artificial intelligence is not there to replace the
work that people do, but to
help them.  that person, not even to
be more productive, but to achieve
things that they would not have been
able to otherwise.  What do I mean by this?
Okay, there's a pedagogical principle
that consists of adapting
teaching to each individual student,
not
the level
of teaching, but the methodology,
the pace in a certain way.
and the theme to emotionally involve
the student.  That is, it is assumed
that the student learns better if he or she is
emotionally involved
in the training.
What's going on?  As a human being,
okay?
The theory
would be
that I would give
each of you a different exercise
based on your tastes.
But of course, what does that mean? Well,
I would like to do this, but I
can't because I don't have the physical time
during the day to, taking into account the
number of subjects, taking into
account the number of students, taking into
account the number of exercises, and
also remember what
each student likes and assign exercises for each
of you, okay?
In practice,
a person cannot, a human
cannot, does not have the physical time to
create all those materials,
but with artificial intelligence, they
can.  That's why, first of all, I
asked you to fill out
a survey for me.
In it I collect your profile, your
goals and your hobbies,
what motivates you
emotionally.
This survey is the one we
mentioned before.  Time I'm going to take it
this way.  We take it here and I'll
put it here for you.  This, obviously,
what I'm doing, so
I'll send it to you later by mail.
So it's important
that you fill out
this survey
so that the artificial intelligence and I
know what you like.
From that moment on
,
artificial intelligence generates
personalized exercises
for each of you.
One,
taking into account
what has been taught in class,
taking into account what you like.
generates personalized exercises
for each of you.
Okay?  That's what the first of
the artificial intelligences in
development does.  Next question.  Next
question.  Premise.
Behind artificial intelligence there
must be a human being.
Artificial intelligence serves
human beings.
Artificial intelligence doesn't command us, it
doesn't order us, but there's a human
behind the artificial intelligence,
okay?  There is a human touch
behind artificial intelligence.  The
human being is me.  Okay?  That is, it's
a tool that automates, but it
automates according to what I tell it to
automate,
and sometimes it can make mistakes and
other times it can't.  These days you've
been sending me questions about, it
's not that artificial intelligence asked me for
this, the
activity statement says this.  And there are times when
I say to you, "No, no, that seems like a mistake."
But there are other times when I say, "No,
no, that's something you have to figure out
because it doesn't seem to make sense, but
if you think about it, it does."
Artificial intelligence is
asking you, for example, to tell it
the overall focus of what you are
explaining.  Okay?
So with this, you find,
well, I haven't told you up here,
okay?
eventual interaction in class.
And from here on, live teaching
is done
through Zoom and the teaching, uh
, let's say the classes
are recorded
on video
and you can watch them on the platform.
Okay, on the
mediumsigreen.com platform.
Okay.  Okay.   Just
a moment, let me come down here.
Okay.
Okay.  And this.
Okay.  Okay.
You can find the activities
to do on the platform that
some of you have already started using:
eval.jocarsa.com.
Okay,
once you get into that platform,
okay?  You enter
the platform and
enter your ID.  It is necessary to
have previously completed the
initial data survey on
hobbies.
Okay, from there you select the
subject,
you select
the
module, okay?  Sorry, you select
unit or subunit,
an activity is presented to you.
You must solve it.
according to the drills
we have conducted previously.
How are activities resolved?
One, you read the statement carefully.
Two,
you take out
a code editor.
You implement step by step what
the statement asks of you.
Four.
and you fill out
the evaluation rubric
in a text document.
Five,
you upload the activity
to the platform, okay?  You upload the
activity to the platform and six,
you hit
the send button and seven.  I recommend
that you re-enter the activity
to confirm that it has been saved.
How is this?  Okay, so next I
come over here,
I go to the one I have locally, which I
have in test mode,
I enter the ID.  In this case I'm
pretending to be Serena, I'm going to, uh,
I'm going to programming, I'm
going to variables
and I'm entering.  Okay, I see there are
saved answers.  There are
saved answers.  In fact, there are two
saved answers.  There should be one, but oh
well, that's okay.  Okay, there are two
saved answers and here I have an
exercise.  Okay, here I have an
exercise.  Well, once you've
uploaded the practice,
a few hours or days later,
you'll find the evaluation.  That
means that once every x days I will
pass a second
artificial intelligence and that second
artificial intelligence will be in charge of evaluating you
and will be in charge of justifying the
reason for the evaluation.   That is
, now I'm going to
tell you how it is evaluated and I'm going to tell you what
you're going to find next.  Just
give me 5 minutes, I have to
go out for a moment, okay?